<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: testtools | Mere Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://code.mumak.net/blog/categories/testtools/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://code.mumak.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-13T23:05:41+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://code.mumak.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Lange]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[testtools moved to Github]]></title>
    <link href="http://code.mumak.net/2013/02/testtools-moved-to-github.html"/>
    <updated>2013-02-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://code.mumak.net/2013/02/testtools-moved-to-github</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
Those who closely follow <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/testtools">testtools</a> development will notice something unusual in the 0.9.28 release: we now <a href="https://github.com/testing-cabal/testtools/">host the code on Github</a> rather than <a href="https://launchpad.net/testtools/">on Launchpad</a>.<br /><br />There are a few reasons behind the switch, but the biggest one is that the ecosystem of tools and services around Git &amp; Github is much, much larger than that around Launchpad &amp; Bazaar. &nbsp;Already, by using Travis (thanks <a href="https://github.com/kampka/">kampka</a>!), I've been able to kill off an old, cruddy, insecure Jenkins installation on my server, and actually get proper testing across all of the Python versions that testtools supports. &nbsp;No more, "oops, I broke 3.2" again.<br /><br />We still <a href="https://bugs.launchpad.net/testtools/+bugs">track our bugs on Launchpad</a>, because Launchpad's bug tracker is still our favourite.<br /><br />Happy hacking!<br /><br /></div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[testtools 0.9.13 released]]></title>
    <link href="http://code.mumak.net/2012/02/testtools-0913-released.html"/>
    <updated>2012-02-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://code.mumak.net/2012/02/testtools-0913-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
It has been a while, but <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/testtools">testtools 0.9.13</a> is finally out!&nbsp;Lots more matchers and bug fixes, as well as improved error reporting. Full release notes <a href="https://launchpad.net/testtools/0.9/0.9.13">on Launchpad</a>.<br /><br />Thanks to <a href="http://jameswestby.net/weblog">James Westby</a>, <a href="http://grahambinns.com/">Graham Binns</a>, <a href="https://launchpad.net/~frankban">Francesco Banconi</a> and <a href="http://rbtcollins.wordpress.com/">Robert Collins</a> for making this release possible.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[testtools 0.9.11 released]]></title>
    <link href="http://code.mumak.net/2011/06/testtools-0911-released.html"/>
    <updated>2011-06-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://code.mumak.net/2011/06/testtools-0911-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
While I slept, <a href="https://launchpad.net/~lifeless">Robert Collins</a> released <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/testtools/0.9.11">testtools 0.9.11</a>. This release is mostly a bug fix release, but the fixes are very much worthwhile.<br /><br />In particular, <a href="https://launchpad.net/~gz">Martin [gz]</a> got our Python 3 support going again, <a href="http://gavinpanella.com/">Gavin Panella</a> fixed up a dodgy Matcher and fixed a bug in how we feed information from fixtures into test results.<br /><br />Also in this release, <a href="https://launchpad.net/~tcole">Tim Cole</a> and <a href="http://sourcefrog.net/">Martin Pool</a> made their first ever patches, for which they have my hearty thanks and congratulations. (The congratulations are also hearty.)<br /><br />As always, it's just so darn <i>pleasant</i>&nbsp;to see so many fine people working together to make an open source project work.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[testtools 0.9.10 released]]></title>
    <link href="http://code.mumak.net/2011/04/testtools-0910-released.html"/>
    <updated>2011-04-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://code.mumak.net/2011/04/testtools-0910-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
There was a bug in testtools 0.9.9 that prevented it from being easy_installed. Tres Seaver has fixed this bug, and I've rolled out a new release: <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/testtools">testtools 0.9.10</a>. Sorry for the inconvenience folks.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[testtools 0.9.8 released]]></title>
    <link href="http://code.mumak.net/2010/12/testtools-098-released.html"/>
    <updated>2010-12-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://code.mumak.net/2010/12/testtools-098-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class='post'>
The announcement is a few days late, but I thought that you'd like to know that <a href="http://pypi.python.org/pypi/testtools">testtools 0.9.8</a> has been released.<br /><br />This is one of our biggest releases, we have fixed <a href="https://launchpad.net/testtools/0.9/0.9.8">a lot of bugs</a>, added experimental support for running tests inside Twisted's reactor and added a stack of new matchers and convenience methods. It's well worth upgrading.<br /><br />We've also got some good stuff in the pipeline, including a full re-working of our documentation, better error messages and still more matchers.<br /><br />The "more matchers" thing is significant. More and more people are starting to use testtools because of the way our matchers let them build domain-specific assertions with rich, useful error messages. We continue to get contributions for basic matchers and for new ways of combining matchers. Also, projects like James Westby's <a href="https://launchpad.net/soupmatchers">soupmatchers</a>&nbsp;show just how useful matchers can be. It makes me think that eventually matchers will become part of the normal way that people write tests in Python.<br /><br />Thanks to <a href="https://launchpad.net/~lifeless">Robert Collins</a>, <a href="https://launchpad.net/~gz">Martin [gz]</a>, <a href="https://launchpad.net/~jelmer">Jelmer Vernooij</a>, <a href="https://launchpad.net/~mwhudson">Michael Hudson-Doyle</a> and <a href="https://launchpad.net/~james-w">James Westby</a> for making this our best release ever.</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
